<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "
http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY app "<application>LordsAwar!</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "June 2008">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.0">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en"> 

<articleinfo> 
	<title>LordsAWar! User's Manual &manrevision;</title> 
	<copyright> 
		<year>2008</year>
		<holder>Ben Asselstine</holder> 
 	</copyright>
	<publisher> 
		<publishername>Ben Asselstine</publishername> 
	</publisher> 
	&legal; 
	<authorgroup> 
		<author> 
			<firstname>Ben</firstname> 
			<surname>Asselstine</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname>LordsAWar! Development Team</orgname> 
				<address>
					<email>benasselstine@gmail.com</email>
				</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author> 
	</authorgroup> 
	<releaseinfo> This manual describes version &appversion; of &app;.
	</releaseinfo> 
	<legalnotice id="feedback"> 
		<title>Feedback Information</title> 
		<para>
			To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or this documentation, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>.
		</para>
	</legalnotice>
</articleinfo>

<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>LordsAWar!</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>LordsAWar</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>Lordsawar</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>lordsawar</primary> 
</indexterm>


<!-- ============= Prologue ============================== -->
<!-- Use the Prologue section to excite the user into wanting to play
     the gmae. -->
<sect1 id="lordsawar-prologue"> 
	<title>Prologue</title> 
	<para>
The entire realm is holding its breath -- war is coming, and the citizens know what that means; cities will be sacked, towns will be looted, and flags will be raised.  There will be a shortage of food supplies, high taxes, and fire burning on the horizon, if not even closer.  The best thing to do is to join the army before getting drafted.  
</para>

	<para>
Several factions will vie for total control of the realm.  Talented generals will be needed to lead forces against the enemy.  Plans will be made, and lands will be conquered.  Heroes will emerge to fight on behalf of their general.  Large seige engines will be constructed and rolled to distant cities.  Great ships of war will take to the seas.   Infantry units will be sent to the front line to face the enemy in battle.
	</para>

	<para>
The future is uncertain.  The lords of the realm are warring.  The lords are a-war.
	</para>
</sect1>

<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
<!-- Use the Introduction section to give a brief overview of what
     the game is and what it does. -->
<sect1 id="lordsawar-introduction"> 
	<title>Introduction</title> 
	<para>
&app; is a turn-based strategy game where up to eight players strive to conquer all of the cities on the map.  The player has three distinct roles in the game:

	  <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
The player acts as a General who controls all of military strategy elements of the game; moving armies around the map, conquering cities and managing the production of new army units.
</listitem>
<listitem>
The player acts as a diplomatic envoy, managing diplomatic relations with every other player.
</listitem>
<listitem>
The player acts as a tax collector, automatically collecting gold pieces from each city that has been conquered.  This pays for the maintenance of army units already created.  The income can also be used to buy new and different kinds of army units.
</listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
</para>
<para>
Army units are arranged into stacks of up to eight.  Stacks are moved around the map through varying terrain; forest, hills, swamp, or water.  Each of the varying kinds of terrain cost the stack some of its movement points.  Some stacks may even have the ability to fly over troublesome mountains.  
</para>

<para>
Some army units are special Hero units.  Heroes sometimes emerge spontaneously in cities at the start of the player's turn.  Heroes can search ruins to obtain gold pieces or magical items, or go on special quests.  Powerful allies often accompany a hero.
</para>

<para>
The objective of the game is to conquer all of the cities on the map.  This is accomplished by producing army units in cities and making ever more powerful stacks to conquer neighbouring cities.  Strategy is employed to know which city, or player to target next, on the way to total victory.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="lordsawar-cities"> 
	<title>Cities</title> 
<para>
Cities are important because conquering cities is the key to winning the game.  Each player starts with one city, or more than one if the game is started with the "quick start" option.  Each city can produce army units that the player can use to attack other cities.  Each player has a capital city that other players can target and take over for bragging rights.
</para>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-what-are-they">
	<title>What are they?</title> 
<para>
Cities appear as castles on the map.  They occupy four tiles on the screen; a two-by-two square.  Army units located in the city fight as a single force when the city is attacked by the enemy.  Some army units will have a special fighting bonus if they are defending a city, or attacking a city.
</para>
<para>
Cities have a name, a set of army unit types that they may create or "produce"; they provide a number of gold pieces to the player's treasury every turn, and they have a defense level.
</para>
<para>
Each city can produce one of up to four different army unit types.  When enough turns have passed the army unit shows up in the city and can be moved around the map as the player sees fit.
</para>
<para>
Production can be viewed and modified in cities that the player owns.  The production in enemy cities can also be viewed if the game is started with the "view production" option turned on.
</para>
<para>
Cities provide income in the form of gold pieces, which happens to be exactly what army units require as their upkeep.  Conquering more cities gives the player more money and enables the upkeep of more army units.
</para>
<para>
Movement in a city that the player owns is the same as moving on a road; it is easy for every army unit to move within the two-by-two confines of a city.  Cities that are adjacent to the water act as a port; a jumping-off point for naval operations.
</para>
<para>
Army units may not move through a foreign city without conquering it first.
</para>

<para>
The defense level for the city is not important and is ignored by all battle calculations.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-explain-the-city-screen">
	<title>Explanation of the City screen </title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-how-they-make-critters">
	<title>Producing new Army units</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-taking cities">
	<title>Taking Cities</title> 
<para>
explain neutral cities here.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-buying-production">
	<title>Buying new production capabilities</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="lordsawar-units"> 
	<title>Army Units</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-how-to-read-a-units-stats">
	<title>How to read an Army Unit's stats</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-units-what-kind-of-bonuses">
	<title>Augmenting an Army Unit's stats</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-combat"> 
	<title>Combat</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-entering-combat">
	<title>Entering combat</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-stacks">
	<title>Stacks</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-order-of-battle">
	<title>Fighting Order</title> 
<para>
...and order of dying.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-bonuses">
	<title>Bonuses</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-example-in-field">
	<title>example of combat in the field</title> 
<para>
...1 on 1 in the field.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-example-in-city">
	<title>example of combat in a city</title> 
<para>
...1 on 1 in a city.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-another-example-in-city">
	<title>another example of combat in a city</title> 
<para>
...8 on 32 in a city.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-heroes"> 
	<title>Heroes</title> 
<para>
how to get more heroes?
</para>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-why-they-rock">
	<title>Using Heroes to your advantage</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-exploring ruins">
	<title>Exploring ruins</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-quests">
	<title>Going on Quests</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-movement"> 
	<title>Movement</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-movement-over-land">
	<title>Traveling over land</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-movement-over-water">
	<title>Traveling over water</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-diplomacy"> 
	<title>Diplomacy</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-diplomacy-advantages">
	<title>Using Dimplomacy to your advantage</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-diplomacy-explaining-the-report">
	<title>Explanation of the Diplomatic Report</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-options"> 
	<title>Options</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-scenario-options">
	<title>Scenario options</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-keyboard-commands"> 
	<title>Keyboard Commands</title> 
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-multiplayer"> 
	<title>Multi-player play</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-hot-seat">
	<title>Hot-seat Play</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-network-play">
	<title>Network Play</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
