<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "
http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY app "<application>LordsAwar!</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "June 2008">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.0">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en"> 

<articleinfo> 
	<title>LordsAWar! User's Manual &manrevision;</title> 
	<copyright> 
		<year>2008</year>
		<holder>Ben Asselstine</holder> 
 	</copyright>
	<publisher> 
		<publishername>Ben Asselstine</publishername> 
	</publisher> 
	&legal; 
	<authorgroup> 
		<author> 
			<firstname>Ben</firstname> 
			<surname>Asselstine</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname>LordsAWar! Development Team</orgname> 
				<address>
					<email>benasselstine@gmail.com</email>
				</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author> 
	</authorgroup> 
	<releaseinfo> This manual describes version &appversion; of &app;.
	</releaseinfo> 
	<legalnotice id="feedback"> 
		<title>Feedback Information</title> 
		<para>
			To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this application or this documentation, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>.
		</para>
	</legalnotice>
</articleinfo>

<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>LordsAWar!</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>LordsAWar</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>Lordsawar</primary> 
</indexterm> 
<indexterm zone="index"> 
	<primary>lordsawar</primary> 
</indexterm>


<!-- ============= Prologue ============================== -->
<!-- Use the Prologue section to excite the user into wanting to play
     the gmae. -->
<sect1 id="lordsawar-prologue"> 
	<title>Prologue</title> 
	<para>
The entire realm is holding its breath -- war is coming, and the citizens know what that means; cities will be sacked, towns will be looted, and flags will be raised.  There will be a shortage of food supplies, high taxes, and fire burning on the horizon, if not even closer.  The best thing to do is to join the army before getting drafted.  
</para>

	<para>
Several factions will vie for total control of the realm.  Talented generals will be needed to lead forces against the enemy.  Plans will be made, and lands will be conquered.  Heroes will emerge to fight on behalf of their general.  Large seige engines will be constructed and rolled to distant cities.  Great ships of war will take to the seas.   Infantry units will be sent to the front line to face the enemy in battle.
	</para>

	<para>
The future is uncertain.  The lords of the realm are warring.  The lords are a-war.
	</para>
</sect1>

<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
<!-- Use the Introduction section to give a brief overview of what
     the game is and what it does. -->
<sect1 id="lordsawar-introduction"> 
	<title>Introduction</title> 
	<para>
&app; is a turn-based strategy game where up to eight players strive to conquer all of the cities on the map.  The player has three distinct roles in the game:

	  <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
The player acts as a General who controls all of military strategy elements of the game; moving armies around the map, conquering cities and managing the production of new army units.
</listitem>
<listitem>
The player acts as a diplomatic envoy, managing diplomatic relations with every other player.
</listitem>
<listitem>
The player acts as a tax collector, automatically collecting gold pieces from each city that has been conquered.  This pays for the maintenance of army units already created.  The income can also be used to buy new and different kinds of army units.
</listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
</para>
<para>
Army units are arranged into stacks of up to eight and are moved around the map through varying terrain; forest, hills, swamp, or water.  Each of the varying kinds of terrain cost the stack some of its movement points.  Some stacks may even have the ability to fly over troublesome mountains.  
</para>

<para>
Some army units are special Hero units.  Heroes sometimes emerge spontaneously in cities at the start of the player's turn.  Heroes can search ruins to obtain gold pieces or magical items, or go on special quests.  Powerful allies often accompany a hero.
</para>

<para>
The objective of the game is to conquer all of the cities on the map.  This is accomplished by producing army units in cities and making ever more powerful stacks to conquer neighbouring cities.  Strategy is employed to know which city, or player to target next, on the way to total victory.
</para>
</sect1>

<!-- ============= Cities ============================== -->
<sect1 id="lordsawar-cities"> 
	<title>Cities</title> 
<para>
Cities are important because conquering cities is the key to winning the game.  Each player typically starts with one city, with the remainder of the cities being unowned.  Each city can produce army units that the player can use to attack other cities.  Each player has a capital city that other players can target and take over for bragging rights.
</para>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-what-are-they">
	<title>What are they?</title> 
<para>
Cities appear as castles on the map display; they occupy four tiles on the screen; a two-by-two square.  Cities appear as little shields on the miniature map.
</para>

<para>
Cities have a name, a defense level, and they provide a number of gold pieces to the player's treasury every turn.
</para>
<para>
The income is in the form of gold pieces, which happens to be exactly what army units require as their upkeep.  Conquering more cities gives the player more money and enables the upkeep of more army units.
</para>
<para>
The defense level for the city is not important and is ignored by all battle calculations.
</para>
<para>
Each city can produce one of up to four different army unit types.  After enough turns have passed the army unit shows up in the city and can be moved around the map as the player sees fit.  Changing a city's production of army units is one of the main ways that a player affects the outcome of the game.  The player can also choose to add a new army unit type to the suite of army unit types that the city can produce; which can cost a lot of gold pieces.
</para>
<para>
Army unit production can be viewed and modified in cities that the player owns.  The production in enemy cities can also be viewed if the game is started with the "view production" option turned on.
</para>
<para>
Movement in a city that the player owns is the same as moving on a road; it is the easiest mode of transportation.  Cities that are adjacent to the water act as a port; a jumping-off point for naval operations.
</para>
<para>
Army units located in the city fight as a single force when the city is attacked by the enemy.  Some army units will have a special fighting bonus if they are defending a city, or attacking a city.  To attack a city, move your army units to an adjacent tile and then attempt to move into the city.
</para>

<para>
Army units may not move through a foreign city without conquering it first.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-explain-the-city-screen">
	<title>Explanation of the City screen </title> 
<para>When the player left-clicks on the city the following screen is displayed:</para>
<figure id="citywindow-fig">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/city_window.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
Shows &app; city window.  Contains a map, with icons for cities we own.  Contains the city name, it's income the army units it may produce and the one it is currently producing.  It also shows the operations that the player can take; like stop production, buy production, vector, raze and rename.
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>

<para>
The most noticeable thing in the screen is the miniature map that only shows all of the player's cities.  At a glance it shows; which cities are producing an army unit (shown by a white shield with an anvil), which ones are not (shown by a white shield without an anvil), and which city the player is currently visiting (shown by a black shield, with or without an anvil).  The player can visit another city by left-clicking on it.
</para>
<para>
The screen contains information about the selected city.  The title of the screen is the name of the city.  To the right of the map the defense level is shown, along with the amount of money in gold pieces that this city provides.  Next is the army unit that is currently being produced, and how many more turns until it becomes available for use.  The set of buttons in the middle of the screen represent the set of army unit types that this city can produce.
Below that are statistics about the army unit currently being produced.
</para>

<para>
A number of buttons appear at the bottom of the screen.  Here is what they do:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para> Stop.</para>
<para>
Stops the production army units in this city.  Stopping production is a good idea if the player's total upkeep is higher than the total income.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Buy.</para>
<para>
Make a new army unit available for production in this city.  Warning: clicking this button will replace the currently selected production unit.
<para>
Buying new army units is a good idea when the player needs an army unit with a particular capability and that capability does not exist in any of the other army units that the city already produces.
</para>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Vector.</para>
<para>
Produce the unit in this city, but have it show up elsewhere on the map.
Vectoring is useful when the player's "front line" is far away from this city.  It can be used to quickly get new army units into far-away battles.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Raze.</para>
<para>
Burn this city to the ground, and make it uninhabitable for the rest of the game.  This operation is only available if the razing policy in the game options is set to "always".
<para>
Razing an own city is useful to prevent it from falling into enemy hands.  It is a last-ditch effort because no player can own the city after it is razed.
</para>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Rename.</para>
<para>
Change the name of this city.
<para>
Renaming a city can be a way of taunting another player.  e.g. The Impregnable Fortress of Wog.
</para>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-how-they-make-critters">
	<title>Producing new Army units</title> 
<para>
Army units come to life in cities after they have been "produced".  Every army unit takes a number of turns to be produced; typically one to four turns.  The city can produce one army unit at a time, for up to four different army unit types; these are shown as pictures in the boxes on the right side of the city screen.
The button that appears to be pushed-in is the army unit type that is being produced in this city.  When there is one button pushed-in, that army unit type's picture appears, with the number of turns left until the army unit appears in the city.  If none of the army unit type buttons are pushed-in, then the city isn't producing an army unit at all.
</para>
<para>
To select a new army unit for production, left-click on it's button.  The button will become pushed-in, and any other army unit type button will become pushed-out.  This will cause production to stop on any prior army units in this city.  This means if the player has one turn left before some dragons are produced, and then the player selects Pikemen, the dragons will not show up next turn.  The player can right-click on each army unit type button to get more information about that army unit type's capabilities.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-taking-cities">
	<title>Taking Cities</title> 
<para>
Conquering cities is important because it leads to the player winning the game.  After fighting the forces in an enemy city and winning, the player is presented with some options about how to take the city:
<figure id="conquercity-fig">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/conquer_city.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
Shows &app; enemy city defeated window.  It shows the operations that the player can take; like occupy, pillage, sack, and raze.
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
Here is what the various buttons at the bottom of the screen mean:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para> Occupy.</para>
<para>
Take the city and leave the production in the new city unchanged.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> Pillage.</para>
<para>
Take the city and cash in the weakest army unit type that the city can produce for gold pieces.  This will prevent that army unit from being produced in that city.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> Sack.</para>
<para>
Take the city and cash in all except weakest army unit type that the city can produce for gold pieces.  The army units that are cashed-in will not be available for production any longer.
<para>
If this button is not available, it is because the city has fewer than two army unit types available for production.
</para>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> Raze.</para>
<para>
Don't take the city; destroy it instead.  This will make the city uninhabitable by any other player.  Other players may not appreciate this course of action.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</para>
<para>
The easiest cities to conquer are the ones that aren't defended at all.  The player can win the city with the weakest army unit.
</para>
<para>
Neutral cities are typically the next easiest to conquer; they are the unowned cities on the map.  Neutral army units never stray from their castle; they never come to the aid of another neutral city nearby.  Athough neutral cities can be active in that they produce army units after an attempt to attack the city fails (this is a game option that can be turned on).
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-cities-buying-production">
	<title>Buying new production capabilities</title> 
<para>
When none of the army unit types that the city can produce are desirable, the player can purchase a new army unit type for production within the city.
</para>
<para>
When the player clicks on the buy button in the city screen the following screen is shown:
<figure id="buyproduction-fig">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/buy_production.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
Shows &app; buy production window.  Contains a list of army unit types that can be purchased.
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
A list of all army units that are available for the player to purchase are shown.  Some of these army units will likely be too costly for the player to afford!   Some of these army units will already be present within the city's production suite; these army units cannot be selected.  Left-clicking on the army unit type button will select it, and show the price at the bottom of the screen.  Army unit type buttons can also be right-clicked on to see the capabilities of that army unit type.
</para>
<para>
After making a selection, click on the buy button to purchase the unit.  Take special care because purchasing a new unit will replace the currently selected army unit type in the city screen!
</para>
<para>
Some army units are not shown because they are not purchasable.  Special units like dragons or ghosts cannot be purchased, and instead must be awarded to a Hero, or already present as production in a city.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="lordsawar-units"> 
	<title>Army Units</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-how-to-read-a-units-stats">
	<title>How to read an Army Unit's stats</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-units-what-kind-of-bonuses">
	<title>Augmenting an Army Unit's stats</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-combat"> 
	<title>Combat</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-entering-combat">
	<title>Entering combat</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-stacks">
	<title>Stacks</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-order-of-battle">
	<title>Fighting Order</title> 
<para>
...and order of dying.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-bonuses">
	<title>Bonuses</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-example-in-field">
	<title>example of combat in the field</title> 
<para>
...1 on 1 in the field.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-example-in-city">
	<title>example of combat in a city</title> 
<para>
...1 on 1 in a city.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-combat-another-example-in-city">
	<title>another example of combat in a city</title> 
<para>
...8 on 32 in a city.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-heroes"> 
	<title>Heroes</title> 
<para>
how to get more heroes?
</para>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-why-they-rock">
	<title>Using Heroes to your advantage</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-exploring ruins">
	<title>Exploring ruins</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-heroes-quests">
	<title>Going on Quests</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-movement"> 
	<title>Movement</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-movement-over-land">
	<title>Traveling over land</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-movement-over-water">
	<title>Traveling over water</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-diplomacy"> 
	<title>Diplomacy</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-diplomacy-advantages">
	<title>Using Dimplomacy to your advantage</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-diplomacy-explaining-the-report">
	<title>Explanation of the Diplomatic Report</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-options"> 
	<title>Options</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-scenario-options">
	<title>Scenario options</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-keyboard-commands"> 
	<title>Keyboard Commands</title> 
</sect1>
<sect1 id="lordsawar-multiplayer"> 
	<title>Multi-player play</title> 
<sect2 id="lordsawar-hot-seat">
	<title>Hot-seat Play</title> 
</sect2>
<sect2 id="lordsawar-network-play">
	<title>Network Play</title> 
</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
